the stress primarily comes from not
taking action over something that you
can have some control over so if I find
that some particular thing is causing me
to have stress that's a a warning flag
for me what it means is there's
something that I haven't completely
identified perhaps in my conscious mind
that is bothering me and I haven't yet
taken any action on it I find as soon as
I identify it and make the first phone
call or send off the first email message
or whatever it is that we're gonna do to
start to address that situation even if
it's not solved the mere fact that we're
addressing it dramatically reduces any
stress that might come from it so stress
comes from ignoring things that you
shouldn't be ignoring I think in large
part so it's Jeff's doesn't come people
get stress wrong all the time my opinion
stress doesn't come from hard work for
example you know you can be working
incredibly hard and loving it and
likewise you can be out of work and
incredibly stressed over that so and
likewise if you kind of use the you know
use that as an analogy for what I was
just talking about if you're out of work
but you're going through you know a
disciplined approach of you know a
series of job interviews and so on and
working to remedy that situation you're
going to be a lot less stressed than if
you're just worrying about it and doing
nothing